one way of framing it is that we are
smack dab in the middle of a global
scale civilization level collapse now if
we do our job right it will be a
transition to something else but right
now we're collapse is a good way of
thinking about what's happening and what
I mean by global scale is that for the
very first time in human history
starting somewhere or maybe in the 80s
all of human beings were roughly and
trained in a single civilization
framework that's never happen before
so so to begin what I would like to do
is I would like to express my personal
thanks to president Donald James Trump
no I'm serious
because the 2016 election did more to
shake good people from the dogmatic
slumbers than any event that I'm aware
yeah it's a it's actually been a very
big deal I've salts a significant
increase in energy is it giving an
increase in a willingness to accept the
fact that the best way to describe our
current circumstances is that should
have up it's actually a deep
insight because it recognizes
simultaneously that things aren't
working and we haven't got a good way of
describing exactly what is going wrong
and that's like the first temperature
real wisdom so it's a good thing that
that's happening we're going to spend a
little bit of time trying to talk about
what we've been doing and trying to put
some frameworks around what should have
sucked up might mean and how we might go
about visioning what a good positive
direction might look like and I'm going
to start I think we just a short piece
and then Daniel will go into some depth
on the nature of the problem and in
forest will actually introduce us to an
example of what a piece of the solution
likely looks like in something that he
calls transcendental design so one way
of framing it is that we are smack dab
in the middle of a global scale
civilization level collapse now if we do
our job right it will be a transition to
something else but right now we're
collapse is a good way of thinking about
what's happening and what I mean by
global scale is that for the very first
time in human history starting somewhere
maybe in the 80s all human beings were
roughly and trained in a single
civilization framework that's never
happened before and then now that
civilization framework is reaching its
end of life and what I mean by
civilization is roughly the things like
the
the axioms the assumptions the
heuristics the models the practices the
institutions that we humans use to solve
problems and to make our meet our needs
so whether this means things like go to
college or get a job at a company and
get paid money to buy food or go to a
grocery store to get food right these
are all the things that our civilization
produces to allow us to solve problems
and get our needs met and an insight and
I think a core thing for more and more
people to really grasp is that our
civilization toolkit this thing that has
gotten is so far this thing that has
produced seven and a half billion people
in a level of capacity and wealth and
well-being that's never been seen before
is itself the thing that is reached its
end it just can't solve the problems
that we're facing and by the way it's
also falling apart under its own terms
but that's a different conversation and
so what we have to do is we have to
figure out first how to unload that
toolkit unload our assumptions unload
the things that have worked so well and
get all the way down to the deep code
and rebuild something kind of from
scratch and we're going to have to do
this very rapidly so this involves
something that we've never done before
as the people it's going to require a
level of vision it's going to require a
level of communion it's going to require
a level of peace that is I mean largely
is considered to be fiction or prophecy
and now it's not now it is in fact
minimum necessary requirements which is
kind of an interesting thing you know
sometimes I find myself sitting Daniel
and I work together in a business and
sitting in the room having a
conversation about business E things and
I'll just reflect and say gosh last
night as having conversations with
people that it's quite like within the
next seven years our oceans will just be
dead and that's the clock and these are
the things that we're dealing with and
we were talking outside the Daniel wants
to make sure that as we're communicating
that people are left here with the sense
of empowerment and not a sense of panic
or fear and what I'd like to convey is a
sense of resolve which is recognize that
we
in fact actually step in and that fear
and panic although they may be a very
natural response just aren't a useful
response okay so that's that's that part
now I think most what we're going to be
talking about is actually pretty
intellectual that is not to say that we
believe that the solution is in fact
even largely intellectual there was a
piece for the mind to play but in fact
some of the questions that came from
Facebook the basic answer is heart so I
think this is a great place to begin the
conversation
I guess publicly one concept that I'd
like to download before I hand off to
Daniel is a framework that a friend of
mine Dave Snowden not Edie Snowden but
Dave student introduced about ten years
ago for thinking about the different
kinds of ordered systems that we find
ourselves in sciences ready this is a
very intellectual framework but I think
we can do it quickly
the first kind of system is a simple
system and this is something like the
way of pendulum swings back and forth or
a game of tic-tac-toe where the phase
space which is the state the set is of
available states in the system is
relatively small at the total number of
tic-tac-toe games and can fit on a pages
not that many things and so even a child
can sit and observe the system for a
while get the whole thing understand
what to do and master it and so that's a
simple system a complicated system is
the sort of thing that we humans our
civilization is very very good at
building and these are things like say
the Boeing 777 or the National energy
grid or interstate highway system things
that are extremely large faces a whole
bunch of states the system is able to
handle so much more that no person can
ever really grasp them in their entire
you could never master them but if you
spend enough time with them you can
build up an expertise and understand
what the states are and how they
interact and if you get a people who are
all experts in the system you can begin
to manage it and that idea this mission
of becoming experts and managing
complicated systems is a kind of a
succinctly of framing what we do what
our civilization is extraordinarily good
at doing
now the thing about complicated systems
that distinguishes them from complex
systems as although the phase space is
very large it doesn't change and so once
you've figured out the Boeing 777 you
can print out the whole manual put it
aside and look it up and then that's
that in a complex system things do
change it's interesting about complex
systems is on the one hand it's only
been about three or four decades that
we've even been thinking about them
seriously like the name is an even more
than three decades old we're just really
beginning to get a handle on what these
things are and how they operate and on
the other hand things like our bodies
our minds or relationships or ecology or
economies those are all complex systems
which is to say all the stuff we
actually care about is complex and a big
part of the game that we've been playing
as people for the past fifteen thousand
years at least has been trying to use
complicated stuff to manage complex
stuff and this generates a real problem
you see in a complex system things like
causation is are almost impossible to
really figure out you can't make
predictions with precision but exactly
what your impact is going to have on the
system feedback loops feed-forward loops
emergent properties new capacities it
didn't even exist evolution these are
all characteristics of complexity and
one of the big problems in some sense a
nature of the the problem we're facing
is that when you have a complicated
system trying to manage a complex system
as the complex system changes which is
what is going to do the complicated
system has become more complicated to
deal with the the failure modes and so
it gets more and more complicated and
more and more complicated until
eventually it's so complicated that you
can't manage it and then it has to do
something that Dave student calls takes
a journey through chaos and chaos is the
force kind of system and we don't like
chaos chaos is generally a very sad
place to be and we might even want to
say that we don't want to take a journey
through chaos but it seems unfortunately
rather unlikely we're going to be able
to do that because every single time a
truly complicated system has to adapt to
a complexity can't manage the way that
it breaks
is it disorderly and it goes through
chaos and then you come back into
authentic complexity so it might be the
case and something to consider that our
job right now is twofold
first is to figure out how to position
ourselves so that we can in fact endure
the chaos possibly even be anti Fraser
to the chaos and you use the chaos to
build something very positive and then
second to do what we can now to envision
what a future looks like that embraces
complexity authentically does that
retain complexity to work with
complexity and build a civilization or
whatever we would want to call it maybe
something completely different that is
directly related to the natural dynamics
of complexity okay so Jordan used the
word anti fragile which means resilient
if we can get the game down a little bit
but more than just resilient it means
that when things come up that are going
to be deviations from the homeo dynamics
of that system it's not only going to
not break but it's going to be able to
learn from them in the systems going to
evolve you mentioned that complex
systems are evolving so complicated
systems are not self-organizing right
the 747 is a designed externally
designed thing as opposed to a
self-organizing an emergent thing that's
another key distinction you notice that
our human civilization systems are macro
economic systems the way we think about
putting the principles of them together
our governance systems especially our
infrastructure are complicated systems
but they interface with the complex
systems of ecology of human psyches of
the social you know human social
dynamics and the behavioral dynamics of
economies and so it's important to get
that our built world or human built
world is not anti fragile it's not
self-organizing right and so it's it is
fragile to collapse and we've seen this
if we look at civilizations throughout
history they didn't all fare well right
and it's important to get that because
since we didn't go through Easter Island
and we didn't go through the collapse of
most of the things that were called
civilizations in the past and in our
life we haven't gone to that at all we
don't actually have an expiry
reenter intuition poor really
breaking down and so it seems like that
just couldn't really happen intuitively
because we haven't been exposed to it
intuition is conditioned by our
experience our intuition is not adequate
right our experiential intuitions not
adequate for the scope of what we face
this is a super important topic and so
when we look at Syria we see that their
complicated system right there their
governance system their infrastructure
has radically collapsed we see that it
was complex dynamics that led to the
collapse of that scenario and the lack
of ability to support life of the people
who are there lots of complex right
there were economic motives there were
all kinds of social and political
motives but there were also droughts
that were most likely the result of
climate change
that led to subsistence farmers not
being able to grow food that led to them
coming into the cities that led to
resource collapse resource Wars that
then collapse a complicated systems
right this is complex system failure
creating breakdown of the complicated
systems that we depend upon so this is
when Jordan saying that our previous
toolkit isn't adequate more complicated
blueprints are not going to get us there
right that's one aspect I want to talk
about another part of our toolkit that
has to change which is our motivational
toolkit right not just our design
toolkit but our motivational toolkit
what we think of as you know the game
theoretic or the behavioral mechanics in
it so we've we can think about phases
that civilization has gone through many
people have brought up the point right
when Gandhi was asked what do you think
of Western civilization he said I think
it would be a good idea and it's
actually a meaningful point right
because he's saying it and Jacque fresco
has famously said this many people's as
long as homelessness is okay and you and
you're going to kind of focus on other
stuff and as long as killing each other
is a reasonable solution to conflict
resolution is it fair to call that
civilized yet or you know is it fair to
call it humanity is it really humane so
maybe civilization and Humana
are terms that we are aspiring to we
haven't got to yet and maybe the birth
of civilization the term actually
deserving of that is what is on the
other side of this chaos if we if we
navigate towards that so when we talk
about the history of civilization
usually we're talking about the history
of empire post agriculture right that's
usually the timeframe that we're talking
about and we we look at phases right
we'll call you know hunter-gatherer
tribes and then groups of tribes and
then fiefdoms and kingdoms and movements
towards nation-states corporations
globalism even though those were
fundamentally different organizational
dynamics for some in group to win at a
competitive game for scarce resources
against some other out group they all
had that in common they were all playing
win-lose games that was fundamental to
their game theory right so in-group
out-group fundamentally zero-sum win
lose game theoretic dynamics so if you
disagree with people or you want the
same resources that are scarce and so
you decide to kill each other as a
solution and you're dealing with Spears
you'll kill some people but not
everybody and not the whole ecosystem if
you're going to race to pull out the
unremovable resources from the ecosystem
fat faster but you are doing it with
axes you'll damage some ecosystems but
not all right but as your tools are
going through exponential increases in
power and the capacity to affect the
world then the capacity to cause damage
will actually leads to a place where win
lose becomes lose lose right when when
you go from stone tools to guns to
missiles to weapons of mass destruction
there is no such thing as winning a war
at that level and so when lose attempt
becomes Omni lose-lose for everybody
right when you go towards racing towards
who can extract the dwindling resources
fast enough with the kinds of industrial
technology that allow us to extract them
so much faster than they can regenerate
that's Omni lose
for everybody so we're going through a
shift where we either have lose lose
motivational dynamics or Omni win-win
and there's no spaces in between we've
never had an omni win-win worldview
right we had win for everybody in our
civilization but usually not even that
it's like when for the ruling class and
the civilization at the cost of the
peasant classes that do all the worth in
the labor force etc so what does it mean
to really recognize with the level at
which we can affect each other because
of exponential technology requires that
we take full consideration for making
sure that we're not externalizing harm
of that effect on the planet that can't
handle the externalization load anymore
so you know we will use the term Omni
considerate and obviously we can't be
fully Omni considered but it's a
directional to our moving in the
direction of considering more so that
there is no externality gap right we can
say that the future of macroeconomics
one of the defining criteria has to be
that the incentive of every agent in the
system and that's every person or group
of people has to be aligned with the
well-being of every other agent and of
the commons and any place where someone
is incentive to do something that
directly or indirectly causes harm
somewhere else you cannot prevent harm
that your incentive well a system that
meets that criteria looks like no system
of economics that we have ever had it's
not Marxism it's not socialism it's not
capitalism it's not a retrofit of any of
those systems either now notice that
exponential tech which means the ability
to affect the world radically more power
into it most people don't have an
intuition that can make any sense of
exponential curves of any kind
exponential curves where the next phase
in the iteration can have as much change
as the entire curve up to that point
what that means is that the way we solve
problems previously is becoming more and
more obsolete faster and faster with
more and more consequence this is this
is a big deal right this way we're
talking about a transition not just an
iteration
and so when we think about exponential
curves in the ability to affect things
where our tools give us more ability to
make better tools faster like we see
with Moore's law and computing like we
see with biotech nanotech or all of
those areas as our ability to impact the
world is scaling up radically our choice
making for how to implement that power
effectively right to implement it Omni
considerately has to be scaling and
right now it's not even close so when
the first technology that was powerful
enough that had portended our ability to
take ourselves out the first existential
tech which was the bomb and you know
Einsteins insights led to the bomb he
said famously it's painfully evident
that our technology is far past our
humanity we have to fix that issue right
we have to make sure that we have
exponential increase in our choice
making capacity and you can you know
Jordan said it almost feels mythic right
like the coming of the end of an age and
the possible emergence of a new age
there it's reasonable right to think of
those metaphors and so if you think of
it in the mythic sense as people as
we're scaling towards having the power
of gods if we don't have the wisdom and
consideration and love of gods and that
power is inexorably self terminating
right so we have to move from
complicated system designed to actually
understanding complexity there's a as
one example of many of our frameworks of
problem solving having to change we also
have to move from thinking that we can
solve some of our problems independent
of or at the expense of others as a
reasonable approach that also has to
change and so where there were local
issues before when the people died on
Easter Island it didn't necessarily
impact everybody right we don't have
that scenario we have these radically
interconnected global issues where the
oceans dying is that everybody issue and
anyone contributing right any nation
contributing to those dynamics ends up
affecting all of us so you know nations
made sense when the level at which we
affected things was a kind of a national
level and we could govern at the level
that we affect things but where we're
affecting things at a global level
we have to really govern and think about
that space right so the idea that there
can be collapsed somewhere and we're
unaffected by it and we get to make it
through that's also an obsolete idea and
on a very short timescale if you look at
the different groups that are looking at
catastrophic risk and existential risk
there's variance and what the timescales
are but they're all profoundly shorter
than most of us think about on a daily
basis how many people here feel that
right feel the sense of imminent shift
right so when you have a system that
where some things are getting
exponentially better more powerful other
things are getting exponentially worse
that doesn't mean the system is going in
either those directions it means it's
destabilizing and you're getting to the
end of that phase you're either going to
get a phase shift down to a much lower
level of organization which looks like
things that none of us want or a phase
shift up discretely to a fundamentally
different set of organizational and
motivational and and even identity
worldview dynamics so that's what we're
here to talk about and explore more
tonight some design principles that are
relevant so I'm going to pick up on a
few of the themes that that have been
raised by my good friends one of the
themes that has been raised as the
notion of complexity and in a way of
thinking of things we can actually say
that these these concepts have
relationships to one another that these
themes come together when we're looking
at complexity how do we deal with
complexity what is the tools that we use
to deal with complexity well there's two
other concepts that come to mind one of
them is simplicity and the other is
clarity these three concepts always
occur together they don't ever occur
separately where there is something that
is complex there's also something else
that is simple and there is also
something else that is clear so the idea
is and to try to reduce complexity into
some state of simplicity or to try to
see it only through the terms of
something which is simple but to
actually use the tool of clarity to be
able to deal with complexity so in
effect what I'm going to
try to do is I'm gonna try to be really
clear about some of the ideas that that
have come forward that we have about
what sort of toolkit can we bring to
bear on the kinds of problems that are
facing us we know that the solutions
that have been brought forward to create
the civilization that we're now in are
no longer adequate for dealing with the
problem and when we try to even identify
what the problem is we recognize that
like life itself it's very complex so
the effort is essentially to try to
bring a kind of clarity to the process
what is the essence of what is going on
how do we how do we understand it how do
we relate to it what ways can we
influence or be influenced by it and so
when we're looking at design when we're
trying to think about okay we're in a
position of having these conversations
about choices about the choices we make
individually about the choices we make
collectively as a community as of
choices we make collectively as a nation
or as a globe and so in effect a lot of
the exercise comes down to what are the
principles of effective choice how do we
choose together how do we align
ourselves so that the choices that we're
making are good choices and what does it
mean to make a good choice how would we
know it how would we recognize it how
would we understand whether the design
that we're proposing to solve a
particular problem is actually a good
design it's something that would create
a solution that is enduring that is anti
fragile that would in effect create a
state of health create a state of
thriving we want to use whatever choices
we make individually to try to move the
society that we're in the culture that
we're in into a phase transition that is
in a sense a healthier way of being and
to do that we would want to of course
have some idea of what health is so that
we can recognize it we want to
appreciate the kinds of dynamics that
create systems that could actually have
a sense of vitality to them that we
would want to be a part of because we
recognize that it's good for our own
lives for our family for the quality of
life that we know we want to increase
that but to know how to do that in a way
that's balanced in a way that is
essentially Omni considerate well that's
a complicated problem
and in order for us to to develop the
tools to deal with these kind of things
in order to have designs that are
essentially good designs we need to even
think about the notion of how design
works what kind of designs are actually
going to be effective in this scenario
and which ones will not be nature has
been of course a very good example for a
design process evolution has in a sense
resulted in the complexity and the world
did we know in a lot of the solutions
that were aware of have been arrived by
a process of evolution evolution as a
design methodology although it is
somewhat unconscious tends to be very
thorough when we're looking at design
for something of a biological nature
like considering just the eyeball right
just this one organ that we have it
isn't that it just solves one problem
figuring out a way to see what's in the
world's and have that information be
something that we can respond to it
actually solves a whole constellation of
different problems simultaneously it has
to be something which is possible to
grow when you're you know born you don't
have an eye and then when you basically
arrive on this planet you have a
functioning organ it had to go from a
state of not being to a state of being
there needed to be some way for the the
organic systems to essentially emerge
with this structure of this organism it
has to in effect the self-healing you
know if I get a piece of grit where I
scratch it or something you know bumps
it or I have something go wrong that
there's a there's an automatic mechanism
that it uses to essentially repair
itself how many of your cameras will
repair themselves you drop a cell phone
in a cracks it's not going to heal it's
just going to stay cracked and in a
sense the kind of the kind of
evolutionary process that is resulted in
the design of this marvelous piece of
technology that in a lot of ways exceeds
anything that we can build today has not
just optimized for one particular aspect
but it's essentially solving a whole
constellation of problem simultaneously
so when we're looking at civilization
design how to in effect recreate what we
mean by the very notion of civilized
what is the essence of the problem we're
actually trying to solve it's not
something that we're going to address by
optimizing for any single particular
function in fact even the notion of
optimization itself is something of a
problem
we don't get to the kinds of solutions
that we need by optimizing for any
single metric or even any finite set of
metrics we need to in a sense know what
are the principles what are the
characteristics that a good solution
needs to have when I'm trying to make
decisions I'm not necessarily go through
some sort of calculus equation to figure
out whether or not it's a good decision
I'm going to say does it have these
characteristics does it in a sense meet
the minimum necessary and sufficient
criteria in order for it to actually be
a solution in the space that it's
supposed to be a part of I'll give you
an example so I I do a lot of product
design I have a company and we make
things we sell them to the commercial
market to the end consumers really and
you know a lot of people that approach
me and say hey I have this great idea I
want to I want to make this thing and I
want to sell it to people and so on and
so forth and you know I look at it and
and you know we have a conversation and
I ask a few questions I ask okay so you
know do we have the materials can we can
we source the stuff that this thing is
made of can we build the tools that that
that are necessary to make this thing
can we train the people to to use the
tools to make the product can we afford
to have you know can we pay people to do
that has anybody thought about the
instructions that are necessary to be
read by the person that's going to use
this thing is there an idea of how
you're going to present it to the market
do you know who the beneficiary of this
work is do you understand all of the the
kinds of relationships that are going to
evolve in the marketplace and how it's
going to change the market have you
accounted for what happens with the
product after a person is done using it
where does it eventually go in the
environment does it come back to the
manufacturer and you recycle it somehow
or another does it end up in a landfill
and when we look at things like
pollution there's a sort of this
realization that pollution happens the
instant that something is made it's not
you know sometime later on when it ends
up in the landfill as soon as we combine
something that nature has no way of
taking it apart we've already become
part of the problem so in effect we need
to think about a much broader set of
questions a much broader set of of ideas
a much broader set of issues and
characteristics in order for us to
essentially identify to recognize
that we are even thinking about this an
appropriate way are we even asking the
right questions and how would we know so
in a lot of ways that the details that
we're trying to get to the things that
are essentially really important how do
we organize ourselves into communities
of people that can collectively
influence some of the situations that
are affecting all of us what does it
mean for us to essentially align our
choices as agents into a way that
actually makes sense what does that mean
when we think about the notion of
civilization in a lot of ways it comes
down to a kind of conversation when I
think of civilization I think of
people's capacity their availability to
talk to one another and the level and
quality of the conversations that are
that are having it's not you know our
current culture has gotten very enamored
with this so-called broadcast process
here I am you know giving this
presentation and in effect you know I'd
like to actually rather than speaking at
you to be having a conversation with you
right but in effect work we've gotten so
used to this method of of providing
information in some sort of bulk
accounts and that we've in effect had
this the sort of method of communicating
that is essentially a top-down way of
thinking and we've gotten very used to
design processes that are very top-down
design process you know we have a
problem we want to solve we figure out a
way to solve that particular problem and
then we work out all the details and
then we you know we deliver it right
sort of a waterfall lifecycle design
what we really need in this particular
point is a kind of design a kind of
conversation the rather than being from
some sort of central single monolithic
point of view has in a sense a kind of
diffused integration it has a kind of
organic quality to it we don't have the
time to wait for evolution to figure
this out and given some of the powers
and capacities that we have developed
technologically we uneffective have
entered into the responsibility of being
responsible for our own evolution being
responsible for our own design so
thinking about design questions in a way
that
neither top down which is maybe accurate
but not precise enough or bottom up
which may be really really precise but
take a long time we find ourselves in a
situation where we need to come up with
design capability design characteristics
that have the rapidity of top-down but
the effectiveness of bottom-up and so in
a sense our exercise is essentially to
develop a set of tools develop a set of
conversations the set of intelligent
building apparatus that allows us to
deal with complexity in a profoundly
clear way so that's what this
conversation is about tonight so before
we get to the questions and answers I
just wanted to bring two more things one
is a strategic framework for how at
least I go about thinking about what I
want to do and how I want to participate
in this thing because I have certainly
noticed over the past couple of decades
that different people have different
proclivities the different preferences
they have different kinds of things that
they're attracted to and things that are
not interested in at all and so there's
no one Pro try this every single person
here is fully responsible for doing
exactly what is theirs to do in this
thing but it seems like there are three
basic categories that things are pulling
apart into an almost temporal so the
first category is the category of the
urgent there are things that are urgent
things we must not let happen over the
next couple of years and those aren't
too hard to guess and unfortunately
getting off too close to them things
like say nuclear war among the great
powers would be the sort of thing that
we would must avoid over the next couple
of years under the number actually of
things that are absolutely urgent and
must be avoided or in fact must it must
happen over the next several years two
three four years and if you're the kind
of person who has the energy and
commitment
and ability to sacrifice to address
those kinds of things that's a good
place to go but if you are don't waste
your time on things that require 15
years of planning just a very those
things are out of match the second
category is a category or a lot of folks
are spending time on right now and this
is in the time frame maybe anchored on
say seven years or 15 years somewhere in
there depending on how things play out
and I consider this to the period of
transition and this is the period where
we do our absolute level best to squeeze
a couple more years out of the current
civilization model to hold us as we
engineer the transition so when we land
it's a soft landing and so something
like say Universal basic income which is
was a question that was asked and is
something that's getting more and more
conscious now is in that category it's
not post transition is transitional if
it works it will get us to the next step
but it will not be the next step itself
and then the third stage is the stage
that force is talking about the post
transitional stage and that's extremely
difficult this is the sort of thing that
to be Raziel to be resilient to
exponential technology is going to
require a level of capability a level
precision a level of design that we we
can barely name and we haven't really
fully figured out how to embody yet and
it's going to take years right so heart
in some sense if you're in the first two
categories your job is to buy time so
the people who are prepared to try to do
the stuff at the post transition
framework can get those things in place
so we're actually have a good thing to
land on and if you're a visionary who
can input to put names against those
things to seek out the people who are
who are equipped to be able to take that
vision and bring it into reality so
that's one piece of material that I hope
is helpful to people in thinking how to
apply themselves the other is the
hopeful side of this conversation and I
had a conversation with our friend Brett
I think maybe yesterday about a dynamic
that's going on a number of different
places and the new this group is
certainly part of that which is what he
will call the shamanic path and he's an
evolutionary theorist and he put it this
way said human beings actually tend to
operate in two modes when things are
going well or actually if things are
going even marginally okay we tend to
just kind of like stay where we are and
run the code that we've already written
and we like that that's really safe
because change is generally a very bad
thing but when things are clearly not
doing well then we actually have to
shift into a different mode and we have
to call up the shamanic energy you know
people sitting around the fire and
talking about things people dancing
ecstatically people taking drugs to be
able to think differently because as
individuals we really can't think we do
not sink as individuals we think as
groups we think as groups in
conversation with each other as forces
saying really learning the art of coming
together in groups that can have these
conversations and rebirthing or actually
calling out in ourselves the shamanic
energy to be able to actually have the
kind of consciousness necessary to do
the things we're talking about is the
thing the thing to be done and the good
news is is that even though we have only
grown up in a time frame where these
sorts of things haven't happened in our
memory we are the ancestors and the
descendants of people who have had that
time frame so it's in us to do it and I
imagine most people here actually
feeling it and has felt for quite some
time all the way down at the cellular
level
so it's tuning into that and figuring
how to recover that thing I think is
also a big piece of the solution
all right so we've got some questions
that have come in both online prior to
this event as well as all of you I hope
have been writing questions as as these
gentleman have been sharing and we're
going to pass around a box in about five
minutes
to collect your questions and then
they're going to be ordered and
prioritized as best as possible and and
shared so please if you haven't already
if you have a burning question that you
would think would be relevant to a large
audience please that jot it down and
that box will go around in about five
minutes
in the meantime we've got some great
ones that have come in online and let's
start right here so there it is how can
I most effectively evaluate and
calibrate my own truth detection process
how can i as objectively as possible
find out if a problem is real or
probably real versus an overreaction or
a misperception about collective reality
or reality itself
first if you have found yourself
responding to the environment let's say
for example you're a moment be very
large number of people who responded to
the 2016 election with some mixture of
anger or fear stop those emotions are
very effective at driving action the
extremely poor at finding truth so relax
slow down
and I'm not saying slow down in the
faces of danger because there is danger
but as our friends in the Marines say
slow is smooth and smooth is fast become
smooth so first if you're not smooth
become smooth nothing else can be good
until you are smooth this is very
important right now
second forced mention an unfortunate
model we found ourselves trained into
largely from birth if you've been
watching television certainly since you
got to went to school which is too
get into a mode of broadcast of being
the recipient of information that comes
from people who you've never met and is
broadcast out to a very large number of
people that is broadly untrustworthy no
matter what the origin source is if it
is broadcast it is broadly untrustworthy
which means that you can listen to it
but you're gonna have to do a lot of
work to make any sense out of it at all
I spent about the last year now
receiving information from hundreds of
descript sources that I painstakingly
curate to make sure they are completely
separate from each other and honestly I
can't make sense of what's going on
right now very well so it's very
unlikely that you're getting news from
three or four sources that you're going
to be able to actually use that to make
sense of what you in particular should
be doing right I mean you may be able to
get really angry about something's going
on nowhere near you but that doesn't
help you so the key is in fact
distinctive for us was talking about
this the way we're going to do this is
we're going to have to begin engaging in
conversations with people we have to get
in honestly we're in a situation where
we we actually have the ability to
engage in conversations with people all
over the world and we can find them in
talk with them and share with them
authentically and listen to what it is
they're actually trying to express
regardless of with their words sound
like to us and relearn the art of
actually creating these new forms of
collective consciousness and that may
sound superficial but it is absolutely
the opposite of superficial it is hard
to do and people are crazy
I mean it's nuts out there and and
people also have crazy ideas like we use
words to meet all kinds of weird things
so it's beginning to build from the
bottom up it is actually the thing that
we're doing so it's not that we're
trying to find the truth so that we can
figure out the next thing to do it is
the thing we are doing and having the
ability to in yourself be able to listen
to things that make you respond
emotional or make no sense to your mind
learn how to ask questions how to listen
to enter into dialogue how to seek out
and find the people who have the thing
that you need to share how to share what
is yours
right now I mean that's a really
interesting challenge how do you not
just run the response or persona tells
you to get people to do the you
want them to do how do you actually
share what is actually yours that you
were here to give that is a fundamental
lesson to learn and so that notion
bidirectionally being able to do that
that is my answer that question
picking up on what Jordan said best
source of information is people you know
in other words rather than trying to get
information from new sources of people
you don't know you don't know the filter
that that information is coming through
right anything that's a broadcast
communication anything is essentially a
one-to-many communication transit
transaction and when I say many I mean
like thousands or more you're going to
have essentially a conflict of
motivation that is essentially there's a
there's a commoditization of attention
and time your heart beats right that
irreplaceable moments in your life which
will never be repeated again okay so in
effect what you which you what you first
want to sort of keep in mind is that we
don't make sense of anything by
ourselves we make sense of things in the
community of people that we know and
trust and in effects you know by knowing
the person that is in a sense has in
their awareness that you're interested
in this particular topic or that they
they have a way of thinking about it
that is very clear that they in a sense
become a resource for you to know what
that information actually means in
context right to have someone be able to
say here's my perspective on it but you
know the kind of perspectives that they
have gives you a lot more information a
lot more sense making capacity than
receiving information from any anonymous
source so the kinds of things that we
naturally do we we hang out with our
friends and we have conversations I'm
suggesting we do that a lot more and
that we do it a lot more deliberately
and that we do it with the kind of
intention that is the specific intention
of seeking insight that we in effect are
trying to see through the perspective of
another individual so that we can
combine it with our own perspective
and have a greater depth a greater
dimensionality of perception than what
otherwise be possible right we have to
two of these organs we have two of these
organs in fact we have this capacity to
take the information that we see in each
of these eyes and synthesize it together
to perceive three dimensions where any
single organ by itself would only see
two and this is a technology this is
actually a very powerful technology if I
wanted to build a radio telescope that
was bigger than the size of the planet I
take the signal that is received at you
know the middle of summer and then I
wait six months and I take the signal
that is received in the middle of winter
and I combine them in a certain way and
I get the effect as if I had built
something that was the size of the orbit
of the earth as an amazing amazing
result it's like this this enormous
multiplicative effect when we seek out
diverse opinions diverse people you
don't want to just talk to people that
you know but you also want to talk to
people that are interesting then in the
sense you have a kind of intuition that
something they say may combine in an
interesting way with something that you
would say to them and it through that
sharing through that mutual experience
that you will each perceive the world in
a way that is more genuine more depth
and that's what we mean to make sense of
something so in a sense get to the point
where we see into it to have insight is
to see into so put your cell phones away
get together for dinner and talk about
some real right I mean that's
basically what it boils down to and
remember what you remember what insights
you have write it down you know put it
put it in some sort of notebook or
something and then the next conversation
the next dinner party that you have
bring out the best of the best of what
you have in a sense come to insights for
and synthesize that to a deeper level
the more you go through this process the
easier it is and the more insights that
you gain more insights that we have into
the kind of designs and the solutions
that will constitute civilization 2.0
I want to add to what these guys said
because this might be the most important
question of the night just to underscore
the importance do we know what's
happening at Fukushima really or how
long we have for coral reefs before we
have to do what right how do we navigate
how do we do collective choice making
when we don't have collective sense
making how do we prioritize it like this
is Jordan has written extensively about
this this is a core existential
civilization issue and individually we
take in information we process it and we
act on it but where we're all
intersecting each other and we're
dealing with macro phenomena we have to
be collectively taking in information
right treating each other as sensors and
collectively processing it and being
able to collectively act on it it is by
definition the case that all
perspectives on reality are going to be
a reduction of reality they're going to
have blind spots that are unavoidable
the only way you start to address them
is having more perspectives and then the
ability to start to integrate and
synthesize those of course was saying
get together and talk to people and both
of them are saying get together and talk
to people that one of the keys was
people who have different perspectives
and different data different Intel
because how many people were really
surprised by the Trump election who were
talking to people about politics that
all were in the same misinformation
bubble that they were in right and
because they stayed within a worldview
protected in group misinformation bubble
the world they thought existed in the
world that actually existed we're really
radically different and so a couple
things I would add is want to know what
the world actually is rather than want
to reinforce your ideas about it because
if your ideas about it are off they will
be maladaptive so want to get
perspective that is
different than and even challenging to
the current way that you see things
critical one step deeper than that is
separate your identity from your
worldview right so that your sense of
security emotionally and your sense of
certainty about certain facts are
decoupled because to the degree that
your ability to not freak out is because
you're fairly sure about something you
will not take alternate opinions on that
alternate perspectives even if it's
wrong and so the ability to have some
sense of inability to not freak out that
is decoupled from being fairly certain
about things is actually really
important one of the conversations that
I've had with these two gentlemen
particularly is that I know that when
they say something that they've thought
about it carefully and so as a result I
can I can put aside whatever beliefs I
have and whatever reactions I might be
experiencing or whatever might my ideas
or thoughts or opinions might be and say
okay I really want to know what this
person is thinking I want to understand
how they are perceiving the world
because whatever it is that they're
saying it means something and and so in
effect a lot of the conversations are
really based upon this idea that we
believe that the other person is saying
something that is meaningful it's
important so in effect we want to engage
that aspect as the essence what is
important ask that question what's
important for you right now what's
important in this conversation what is
important for us to say to one another
so that we each have a more
comprehensive view of what reality
actually is this whole thing about
having opinions and perceptions and
stuff like that there is a always going
to be this filtering process nature in a
senses is going to be represented to us
through the filters of our perceptions
and our biases in effect we need to get
skilled at knowing what our biases are
and
being around them uncovering the blind
spots seeing around the corner of things
we're behind you in effect we are at a
civilization level trying to uncover and
to compensate for sociological blind
spots things that are blind spots at an
even bigger scale but in order to do
that we have to develop some new skills
we have to develop some listening skills
and listening skills in the sense says
what is the essence of what's being said
here what is truly important what does
this actually mean what are the
implications of this and so in effect
when we start to to really codify our
communication process on this basis when
we start to think about things in the
sense of okay I want to get to the
essence of this so that I understand it
really as it is as it actually is not as
I would have it be but as it in a sense
needs to be responded to you know when
things are going wrong the first
principle I heard in management class or
training or whatever was stop look see
and tell the truth this goes back to
what Jordan was talking about when you
said first thing you want to do is slow
down in order to get more insight and
more depth you want to slow down and
sink into the truth sink into the
feelings of what your nervous system is
actually telling you there are an
enormous number of tools that we have
built in forever blind spot there are a
couple of - winnings - things that are
good for everything that's good there's
actually a couple of blind spots so we
need to know how to navigate this the
way that we know that way that we
navigate through the minefield of what's
possible this is slow down you don't go
running through a minefield that tends
to get you blown up so go slow so forest
Daniel Jordan what I'm hearing you say
is one the importance of these sense
making tools both as a collective as
well as individuals and interesting how
that as a process leads to empathy it
leads to more
deeply understanding the other this next
question is about building new models
and make old models obsolete without
creating absolute chaos is that possible
and if so how I think I can take that so
when we're looking at large system
design you know like let's say you have
a an operating system you know it's a
very complicated piece of software and
for some reason ro that you need to
change it and you want to make sure that
you actually have a computer that
continues to work because you need it
you know to do things while these
changes are going on it is possible to
do that it's a technique called
refactoring where you basically are
partitioning the source code and you're
working with you know segments of it
which are keeping the whole system
operational and rerouting signals across
the path that you're trying to fix so it
is possible to do this but it takes an
awful lot of skill right if you are
essentially trying to recreate an
operating system of course the easy way
to do is to trash the old one and start
from scratch and create the new one but
oftentimes this isn't actually a very
good idea because what happens is that
it throws out the baby with the
bathwater all the problems that the old
system actually effectively was a
solution for have to be addressed again
from scratch and a half the time we
don't even know what those problems are
what those solutions actually you know
what the techniques of solving those
problems will actually work so our new
system may not actually be an
improvement it might solve this set set
of problems over here but all of these
things that used to work a broken so in
effect when we're looking at system
design part of the things that we want
to do and we're trying to morph a large
complicated system is to first of all
try to you know look at the picture of
what its functionality actually is what
problems does it actually solve what are
the assumptions that were made that may
be different now well what are the
assumptions that were made that are
still true that we need to in a sense
continue to uphold you have clarity
about those kinds of things then you can
start replacing components one at a time
or you could start basically going
through the system and using the
components of the old one to build a new
one having a clearer sense of what a
successful architecture looks like means
that stomachs
you understood the old architecture and
understood it well enough to understand
what problems it was a solution for and
what things it was not a solution for so
that when you're designing the new thing
you're in a sense encompassing and
incorporating all of the learning and
all of the knowledge of the thousands of
programmers that came before you at
piggyback on that the answer to the
second question depends upon how good we
are the first question right our ability
to understand the nature of the problems
well enough on force was describing how
many things in I've all simultaneously
optimizing for one of the challenges
with the issues is that when we get
scared and we want to go fast and we
don't understand the problem space well
enough in addressing some of it we might
be externalizing issues and even more
problematic way and so we can see like
getting scared about climate change and
so we need we need to address
temperature one metric right temperature
is a big metric or that's the first one
for them so geoengineering in a way that
has potentially huge externality load
and doesn't address any of the causal
dynamics where there actually are
solutions that address the causal
dynamics is the kind of thing that
happens if you don't sends me well
enough and then you're in a rush right
to get through so it's it's critical to
actually keep coming back to that right
a problem well understood is half solved
in engineering after is emitted more
deeply we can understand that the better
knowing what questions ask a couple more
things on so the question was based off
of the Bucky fuller quote we don't try
and fight the existing system but build
new ones that are fundamentally more
adequate meet the needs better that
obsolete the old system and they just
become then a strange attractor right
because they're they're more selective
so that's the topic of prototyping right
civilization prototyping this is one of
the critical things that has to happen
that with people in here who are focused
on eco villages and intentional
communities all the way up to city
scales right and what would be the
minimum viable scale to start produce
by being a different economy a different
governance a different materials economy
a different set of social dynamics and
coherence and that's the kind of get a
sense of what is actually potentially
viable in in real instantiation and then
to the extent that it is successful
model be able to reverse engineer that
becoming more wide you know then there's
also the forward engineering of how do
we take civilization wide dynamics that
we can make iterative shifts on that
move the whole system forward and one of
the key dynamics is move it forward
towards more health in a way that
increases our capacity right that up
regulates our collective capacity to
answer that question better in the next
iteration good I actually have a very
different angle and it's what I think
the experts really nice care like
historically whenever we go through a
major transition there are two failure
conditions that leading lead to things
being very bad the first has to do with
the way the elites relate to the
transition so think about for example
the American Revolution the French
Revolution and the collapse of the Roman
Empire in each of those characteristics
the elites related to them transition
very differently in the collapse of the
Roman Empire the elites simply refused
to allow a transition to occur until the
mismatch between their system and the
complexity gotten so high that it didn't
that go to what I would consider to be a
good representation of absolute chaos we
need to avoid that like a plague and so
finding ways to get some portion of our
elites to be able to have a
consciousness of the necessity of being
deliberate about change is extremely
important but if you think about the
American Revolution at least in the
United States along the coast in the
colonies a pretty sizable function of
elites who we now know as the founding
fathers were willing to step into and
take leadership in making that change
happen now the other failure condition
comes from the fact at the end of the
day we're all monkeys
we're primates right we've gotten pretty
good at not killing each other in this
room and staring and being quiet because
we've trained really hard at doing that
but
as civilization starts to break down we
go right back to being 8 and the way
that apes don't freak out is when some
of the apes seem to know what the
is going on and they don't freak out all
right so when things go crazy you're
going to people you'll start looking
around if I who seems to have their act
together have your act together if the
emergent leaders is the second piece
right the people who have done the work
to be able to hold fast and not panic
when things begin to break apart that
other people will look to and say where
is the anchor what's going on here and
if we have enough of those people
embedded in what's happening even as
things fall down they don't go to
absolute chaos actually very interesting
it's not an objective function we've
seen some experiences where monetary
systems have completely vaporized people
have had a hard time eating there's been
fighting didn't go to absolute chaos
because something held the fabric
together right people certain emergent
leaders are willing to step up and say
no we're still going to be civilized
we're still going to hold this thing
together that's the other answer to it
so the architecture in the mechanics and
the thinking the process all very true
but at the foundation if you want to
keep these molecules from tearing each
other apart you know be the person you
want to be simply teeing up the next
question awesome Jordan so so let's get
into the how of that so this next
question is how can we realign
everyone's sense of purpose towards the
well-being of all and away from the
self-interest of the market economies so
that we actually wholeheartedly
cooperate and even innovate with such
transitions how do we get there as
humans
so it is necessarily iterative the
answer is necessarily iterative one of
the things is there's a dialectic of
different things that you're hearing in
the group which is hey things are more
eminently collapsing then you're aware
of on a day-to-day basis when you're
thinking about cleaning the house and
paying the bills etc so there's an
urgency in that at the same time we're
hearing don't react too fast with
urgency and slow down what that means is
a shift of attention from other less
critical stuff to the topics that are
actually at hand because you get that
they're real I know how many people have
watched the videos of Richard Fineman
talking about space but one of the
things he does is beautiful is he's like
when you think about the vast distances
of space and you think about the number
of stars that we talk about like really
think about and it's really there it's
hard for us on planet to think about 400
billion stars in our galaxy it's not
just hard it's actually impossible but
to the degree that you try and then
that's one tiny galaxy to the degree
that you try you're being expands it's
hard for us to think about the
well-being of everything in our personal
choice consideration set and it's hard
for us to get that the civilization that
we have known and that the people we've
respected have known is coming to an end
and that the solutions aren't within
that wisdom set it's actually super hard
to get that but you can write as you
start to as you start to think about it
you can actually get oh wait exponential
growth materials economy extracting
resources faster than they replenish
find that plan that just actually
doesn't enduringly work that's fairly
simple math right you can start to
educate about those things and maybe we
don't know exactly what the timeframes
are but that this current civilization
set is shifting and se-ra if I take that
seriously if I really take that
seriously what do I do differently well
I'm going to allocate more time to
getting more educated I'm going to
develop my thinking and sense making
frameworks one of the things we didn't
to earlier as well we're talking to
people and when for said he takes
seriously when Jordan or I say something
because we've thought about it doesn't
mean he agrees with all of it right and
it doesn't mean that he rejects all of
it means he has an ability to have
analytic thinking and really critical
thinking in parse is this true is it not
true how do we know those are skills
that are developable everybody has to
develop and then synthetic thinking well
that seems true and it seems quite
different than another truth how do
those actually fit together right so the
ability for analysis and synthesis
there's more than that that's necessary
but developing those frameworks and
putting data into those frameworks and
putting more time into the entire thing
but so how do we develop the care right
if you really think about and get that
your own success and the success of your
family is not insurable independent of
the success of the whole if you get that
that is true in the time frame of your
life and your children's life and in
trying to ensure their success
independent of the success of the whole
it will fail and if when you say that
once more that's a really important
point they're trying to ensure our own
individual success independent of or
even at the expense of the success of
others of the whole is not a viable
strategy and yet it was something that
seemed viable for a very long time and
so it's easy to kind of fall back on
that intuition but to get that it's a
fundamentally different time so so
people can get that intellectually but
how do you get them to be that
I'm going to give dad a time to think
but throwing something out that's part
of the conversation didn't mentioned it
that this notion of win-lose was seemed
like a viable strategy for a very long
period of time I'm actually gonna make a
stronger statement that for effectively
all of evolutionary history up until
like a couple weeks ago it was by far
the best strategy it was the absolute
best strategy if you didn't do that you
were going to be selected against and
somebody else's children going to be the
children who populated the world it's
really important to keep that in mind
like evolution really really really
wants us to struggle with other things
to survive but now we're in a situation
where things are changing so the
magnitude this changes not just in the
sense that our civilization is
collapsing right the other side is well
number daniel mentioned it we're
reaching a point where there's going to
be a pivot and it's not they're going to
go up or down if it goes down it goes
way down because up it goes way up and
the people who talk about abundance
aren't wrong
we actually have created so much
capacity that the kinds of things that
we have been struggling over for
hundreds of thousands of years are no
longer meaningful and so for example you
guys are I assume reasonably familiar
with this notion of technological
unemployment it's also getting a lot of
press in the Bay Area in places like
that that things like self-driving cars
are going to unemploy 1.5 million people
in the next decade and that robots are
going to take everybody's jobs now if
you're on the scarcity mindset that's
very scary and being unemployed is very
bad but if you flip it around what that
means is that we don't actually need
people to work that much anymore in fact
in some sense in the next 20 years but
do our things right nobody needs to work
anymore and we actually have to figure
out how to apply ourselves to something
completely different so we're in the
process again of watching this old
structure begin to fall apart and as
Dana said it's going to be iterative
right things like universal basic income
or a nice transitionary piece and there
will be other pieces as well that will
begin to buffer the feeling of scarcity
in a way that begins to allow people to
have actual material freedom to not to
have to
they have to go out and fight dog and
dog and each dog inside the workplace to
survive and then in the mean time we're
in the process of trying to figure out
how to build structures that are
designed for abundance which is a very
different thing
I mean abundance is a completely
different framework of how we go about
doing things by the way it's non-trivial
no purpose for example is a big problem
you think about it right now we have
this really nice mesh where you work to
survive they glue together all right if
I pull that apart and I make it okay
well you don't have to work and you can
still survive where's purpose fit into
this most people get their sense of
purpose by being valuable to other
people by doing their job and creating
something in the world but if you're no
longer working and you're still
surviving that's actually terrible that
will destroy things if you don't have
some way of actually generating purpose
in different mechanism so there's
problem designing post-transition
designing for abundance is a spiritual
it's a psychological it's an economic at
the technological process it is another
way of saying the new toolkit that we're
trying to build so I'll tell with
someone helpful can I pick off of that
so
so Georgie is the work Jordan used the
word purpose and I think it was an
entirely appropriate choice there is
these three concepts purpose value and
meaning okay and those again are three
things that go together but are distinct
right they are three concepts that we
tend to conflate a lot when we talk
about how do we create an economy we're
thinking about value systems we're
thinking about money as a value system
or you know an exchange medium of some
sort or another right
whereas when we're talking about you
know jobs and you know what is our
function in life what do we do you know
you come to a party and you ask okay
well what do you do what's your job and
when we move into a situation that's
opposed a post-scarcity economy we're
looking at an abundance economy of some
sort or another the usual ways of
thinking of defining our lives in terms
of purpose or in terms of value just
aren't going to work because it's not
going to be about that it's going to be
about the meaningfulness of life
meaningfulness is deeper than value or
purpose the notions of value and purpose
are relative to the notion of
meaningfulness so if we're going to in a
sense come to you know some sort of
alignment where we're basically saying
okay how do we as individual people move
beyond this economic actor model where
we're basically having some sort of
exchange medium and that this exchange
process is how we create survival how we
create some sort of you know thing that
is essentially providing food and
shelter and all the rest of that dough
if we come up with a way of using our
technology that manages to provide food
for every living person on this planet
of which we actually have or technology
that allows us to provide shelter for
everybody which we actually also have
that really it becomes a question of
thinking about it differently right we
we in a sense incorporate a kind of
non-economic foundation into creating
choice alignment and how do we do that
well we don't do it by trying to have a
purpose for everybody that we know we're
thinking in terms of how much of a
dollar value each person has you know
how much is your net worth isn't a very
meaningful conversation but on the other
hand you're talking about life
experiences or what's important to you
right now
or what sort of insights that you've had
from an experience that you had last
week those are the things that create
true connections and in effect if we're
going to move into an economy of
essentially some sort of post scarcity
sort of situation it's going to be based
on a meaningfulness principle rather
than on a purpose principle or a value
principle and this is a key concept this
is something I believe to be a necessary
aspect of how to think about this Jordan
mentioned phases that there's a
transition that we're in and there's
urgent stuff that allows us to keep
figuring stuff out there's a transition
there's a post transition the transition
phase is fundamentally different than
the phase it's transitioning from and to
is a key insight will maybe get to that
more later but to answer this question
of how do we increase the connectedness
of the sense of self and the sense of
reality and increase the care awareness
etc how do we do that we said it was
going to be iterative so one design
criteria is that the post transition
phase that actually has to be everybody
and we mentioned antifragility in the
presence of exponential technology we
can't actually put exponential
technology back in the bag that that's
just an inexorable thing that those
capacities are there now when you think
about someone who you know we see goes
and does a mass shooting that seemed
kind of unprovoked they have the access
to a gun and especially say an automatic
gun they can do more damage in that
process than if they had the access to
just a knife right and so now as we take
exponential technology where you think
about the first really catastrophic
technologies we had very few people
could have access to like nuclear
weapons as you move into decentralized
exponential tech and we're very small
numbers of people can have really
catastrophic actions the Omni
consideration and choice making has to
be universal not just some people
because there's no longer ruling class
that then has all the power and everyone
else who doesn't
and so that's part of the post
transition design criteria and it's a
really deep big deal criteria to think
about so for instance most the time that
person who goes into the mass shooting
the neighbors say we didn't really know
them right they were quiet they had
themselves they were a shut-in and so
they could be developing in their
loneliness in their psychopathology with
nobody noticing it that doesn't work
right in the future so how do we move
too connected enough civilizations that
everyone is is actually connected to
other humans meaningfully that others
are connected to them those are going to
be key design criteria but while we say
everyone Romney considered as part of
post transition it doesn't take everyone
for us to get there right this is the
iterative it takes some people building
capacities that start to change game
theory dynamics it's so you know the
person who goes and kills a whale on a
fishing boat because that whales worth
hundreds of thousands of dollars or a
million dollars dead and alive it's not
worth anything it doesn't necessarily
mean that they are whale hating hating
beings right it might doesn't even mean
that they actually feel okay with it it
means that there's a game theory that
doesn't have everyone's incentive and
everything else is well being aligned
and they don't know how to feed their
kids otherwise right or they don't know
how to get ahead in whatever set of
dynamics so can you have those game
theoretic dynamics at scale and have
everyone get there No so how do we have
small groups that start to coalesce and
work on changing those things that
affect and condition human experience in
human behavior at scale like media right
like I like education like economics
that that's a key part of the
understanding it takes everybody but not
at first so we've got some really juicy
brilliant questions from the audience
and about 25 minutes the rapid-fire
through them so here's what we're going
to do for this final round I want all I
want you to really tune in if this is
your question and if it's your question
jump on it and answer as concisely as
you can and we'll move on to the next
one so we get through through some
really good content here
so this first one's a bit of a challenge
this first one is a challenge to guide
us through a visualization on how the
perfect storm unfolds to guide us
through this transition in the best case
scenario to reach an intelligent
collaborative sustainable system model
and particularly help us visualize the
best case scenarios steps that unfold to
get us there no pressure you want this
to be fast go for it turn i made that we
need in order of magnitude between 5 and
10 as significant as the trim pocalypse
to have enough of an impact on people's
consciousness to cause enough people to
detach from their existing dependence on
legacy systems and be willing to take
the risk to jump into novelty space but
if it's more than 10 or 20 times as
large as different pocalypse that begins
to create negative cascade effects so
look at something like ideally we would
have some kind of very significant
economic collapse that would be
best-case scenario like if we could
imagine having hyperinflation where all
dollars are worth nothing tomorrow
that'd be a godsend that would actually
move almost everybody in - oh this thing
that sucks anyway it doesn't work
anymore let me be an experimenting on
the ground without things blowing up
right blowing up is bad imaginary stuff
going away is good so that's a good good
rule of thumb true degree to which you
can get on the order of about 250,000
people beginning to interconnect with
each other and also connect with at
least 12 people on an individualized
basis so that's about three million
people in a meshwork building the kinds
of practices that we've been talking
about that's probably critical mass in
the United States globally it's a
different story and has all kind of
different rate dynamics I don't know
exactly how it plays out there that's a
decent framework though so if you can
imagine scaling this - how many people
here about 300 so scaling this by two
orders of magnitude three doors of
magnitude that's probably the right kind
of framework to be able to maneuver us
across a transition the other big piece
that would be fantastic as I mentioned
we could get a critical mass of Ely in
the next two or three years that's where
things get very sketchy we don't have a
lot of time for that we need to get a
critical mass of elites to be able to
actually be willing to take the risk
that the games a one is going away and
they're going to be the folks who are
going to make the next game happen we
might be able to do without that but
probably not I have a quick one so in
the intermediate transition phase
imagine the world that basically doesn't
have any intellectual property taxes and
then for the long game imagine a world
where everybody understood the full
meaning of this simple idea love is that
which enables choice you really get that
if you really really get that if you
live by that principle if everybody in
the world understood that thoroughly the
world would and would absolutely be a
better place as cliche as it is teeing
up the next question you talk about
forming a collective that's aligned in
feeling deeply interconnected what is
the toolbox to keep us accountable to
that state specific actions we could all
be doing to keep ourselves accountable
to really living in that state of
interconnectivity what it is whatever
you want to call it so we have this idea
that we want to maintain a particular
condition and there was a question that
was asked about you know who's going to
be the enforcers of the loss who's going
to make the loss and this question
strikes me of being very similar in some
respects how do we maintain an integrity
state we can't do it by having a special
class of people that is essentially the
enforcers the police you know that's
just another version of the Stanford
Prison Experiment and though it moves
very slowly it ends up very ugly and you
can't do it by basically trying to have
everybody become the policeman and
watching everyone else that basically
erodes what there's a sense of
individual sovereignty and privacy it
makes you essentially subject to the
tyranny of the consensus and in effect
you end up not being able to do anything
at all because there's always going to
be somebody out there is going to
disagree with the basic premise of what
you're talking about so in effect we
need a third model we need something
that is neither you know the sort of
top-down kind of structured
organizational model of trying
create consensus or we're essentially
the sort of bottom-up thing which is
just you know take so long that no one's
ever gonna actually come to agreement
before the problem in crisis is already
bad right means something that's faster
than that and yet not necessarily has
the disadvantages of a top-down
technique the kind of model that comes
to mind for me is is sort of this
peer-to-peer relationship that computers
can set up that we add you have a
protocol of communication and if neither
computer is is you know disagreeing
about the protocol that an effective
transaction happens information moves
across one machine to another well
nobody is essentially the enforcer of
the protocol if you don't speak the
protocol if you don't know how to speak
the language you don't end up
communicating right the transactions
that are necessary to to move resources
around just don't happen because nobody
wants to talk to you so in effect the
real thing here is is that you can't
enforce communication but by having
communication by you know learning the
language and learning to develop some
sort of consensus technology of having
the conversation that that process tends
to enforce itself Mother Nature doesn't
need some enforcer to enforce natural
laws to in a sense create coherency it
just happens it's just part of a system
it's something that's built in and in
the same sort of way we want to look at
having the integrity of the system
having the integrity of the civilization
having the anti fragile characteristic
be something that's intrinsic to the
process itself that if a crime was
performed that the action of the crime
is its own worst punishment for the
person performing it that's what we're
looking for
wonderful so this i'm really glad this
next question was asked is it was
something that we all face in putting
this event on is gaining a holistic
perspective we've talked about the
importance of diversity we've talked
about the importance of women leadership
in this new phase that we're going
through and yet here we sit right is for
white men and so how do we gain that
holistic perspective how do we continue
to really encourage diversity and ensure
diversity as we're building this new
civilization this new system
I think I want to make one correction
it's not just that it's diversity it's
that it's integration right if we just
have everything the same you don't have
enough integration there's not enough
variation in the system and if you have
just an emphasis on diversity then you
end up with so many different points of
view but no integration that doesn't
work either you want to have something
which is essentially an integration of
enough diversity that essentially you
have really encountered reality if
you're trying to solve a problem and you
only understand part of what the problem
is because you've only exposed yourself
to that you haven't learned the language
of the solution you haven't become a
vehicle to receive and perceive what a
solution would look like so when effect
part of it is is it by embracing
diversity by embracing other points of
view we encounter the language of the
problem space and we become the kinds of
people we become the kinds of
individuals but when we have the insight
we can grasp that feeling and turn it
into a form we can write down the answer
because we know the language of the
problem space we have made ourselves an
expert in the kind of spaces that the
solution existent without going through
the work of actually having the
encounter with the problem without
having exposed yourself fully to the
nature of what the real situation is you
know we talked about Brett earlier a
person that has deep evolutionary
biological experience he's a person that
I view as crucial to informing me about
the kinds of issues that occur at a
biological level because without
accounting for those kinds of things our
solutions are incomplete we in a sense
need to understand the full
ramifications of the problem which means
that we we need to have Omni
consideration means we've got to
basically see from enough perspective so
that we can combine and synthesize
something that our intuition can
actually speak to and our intellect can
grasp
down you know in tune in Daniel Jordan
tune in music so in biology we have this
topic of an adaptive landscape so in in
a landscape you've got multiple peaks
and multiple valleys so as nature's
evolving and we see increased orderly
complexity and kind of a movement of new
emergent more
phlex creatures right with humans kind
at the end of that chain so far
viruses are still evolving to right
corals are still evolving to there's a
whole bunch of different things that are
adaptive and then there's some things
that are not adaptive the same is going
to be true in the future of civilization
it's not going to be a homogeneous here
is the worldview or here is the
aesthetic that everyone has there will
be an adaptive landscape of a number of
ways of being a number of aesthetics a
number of ways of thinking about things
in problem-solving that are all adaptive
that are all functional that all meet
the necessary and sufficient criteria
for a civilization that's viable and
that means that there can be meaningful
relationship across them right not just
inexorable and unrecoverable dysfunction
between them so it's like do we want
diversity well some the kinds of
diversity that lead to inexorable
breakdown in conflict we don't want
right but there's a truth part in those
elements that we need to be able to hold
the kinds of diversity that lead to
multiple perspectives that lead to
synergy and emergence is critical so
synergy across a bunch of the same thing
doesn't really have it all right synergy
across homogeny you don't get very much
emergent property so this is it you know
this is a key dynamic one thing I would
say about it is so how do we seek out
different perspectives we have a friend
who just did his PhD dissertation on
studying higher stages of human
development within which as soon as you
can say that it bothers people right
what does it mean higher stage and yet
development isn't nothing right and one
of the key things that he identified was
something that had been previously
thought to be a key definer which was
perspective taking the ability to take
multiple perspectives was less relevant
than perspective seeking the ability the
the predisposition to seek lots of
perspectives and then the capacity to
actually do it well and then the ability
to synthesize across those but the most
critical part that they identified was
the impetus to actually seek other
perspective so this is important one
thing else I'll say about it is it's
hard
notice how many times has happened for
you where someone has a worldview that
actually bugs the out of you right
that where there's something that you
feel is sacred that it seems like
they're their worldview doesn't care
about them could even damage and you're
just willing to inside go to war with
them but again we just define that
moving forward all wars are lose-lose so
what does it mean to be like okay so
what how do I deal with this so one
thing I would say is to just actually
sit in that we have to and figure it out
as a part of it actually take it back
from wonderful Jordans been burning here
and we want to move on so you have a
quick 30 second out of one move on
you've got a lot that I think you've got
something current ideas before there are
no necessary value conflicts Daniel was
just asking a question if you have
somebody that seems that they value so
Placido know something there's no aspect
of those values which necessarily are
mutually exclusive have that as an idea
and try it out
you'll recall Daniel you mentioned
emergence and you're often sharing that
principle and so the question is can we
rely on emergence can we do the work
individually to be available for
emergence to happen and if we do that
will that allow things to transition
smooth and fast enough or is there
something we need to be doing in
addition to that to bring about this new
civilization that's actually a formality
perfect
right I'm serious I need to actually
think about that I think that we can't
we can't rely on the notion of emergence
I think that if we try to rely on the
notion of emergence that we are in
effect you know having a kind of false
hope we have to work to create that kind
of awareness because there's there's an
effort that's involved between here and
there
I think that a virgin's will actually
happen but I think there will only
happen if we don't take it for granted
exactly the same end result which is
it's not it's actually the question is
not well formed that's not the way to
think about it
the way to think about it is to tune
into who you are and what you're here to
do and do that completely and if
everybody did that do you think that
would be enough to guide us through this
transition it doesn't matter yeah I
think that's agree with Jordan on this
is it is it going to be enough to get to
the transition is an unanswerable
question for anyone right now we're
trying really hard to just identify the
concepts that we think might be the
attributes of what a solution might look
like what characteristic does a solution
need to have that list that this
particular point is unbounded we don't
know whether everything on it is
necessary I don't know whether it's
sufficient we know it's important to ask
the question of what sort of
characteristics are so what sort of
things do we need to develop you know I
think you're right Jordan is the
question to some extent is not well for
but it's interesting I will spend some
more time thank you bye
which knowing forests means you will
write a definitive essay on in the next
48 hours in an email
that's the three people will ignore it I
hope which is so getting into
really practical daily ritual what would
you recommend as a daily ritual practice
for healing and the self work necessary
to be fully available at this moment
meditation is important if you don't
spend a little bit of time by yourself
getting to know who you are if you don't
spend some time basically learning what
is the vehicle that is your life you
know you got to spend at least a little
bit of time to yourself every day
usually first thing in the morning if
you if you've become truly self aware if
you know the influence that people have
on you because you know who you are in
the absence of all influence then you
can begin to account for the effect that
you have on other people which is layer
in the other side of that which is
friends friends are hard like friends if
you have not yet figured out how to
actually have friends that's the next
thing and if you have by the way there
are a lot of people who haven't figured
that out and we most people just play
next to each other
nobody knows people very people know how
to play with each other seriously like
holding people to the standard of doing
with what he just said right holding
this was the standard of it absolutely
not holding back from being exactly who
they're supposed to be is what a friend
supposed to do that is hard so if you do
this and you do that I think you've got
about as good an answer you're going to
get probably when Jordan said on the
last question work on becoming who you
are here to be an offering doing what is
yours to do and that's really it that is
all of you right it is not purely in
elective element or heart development or
will developments or personal or
interpersonal it's all those things and
emergence happens at the intersection of
all those happening right so if is it
relevant to work through childhood
traumas that make us shut down or not
willing to face certain things or create
certain kinds of emotional
predispositions that lead to cognitive
predisposition yes it is necessary is it
sufficient no is it necessary to develop
our critical thinking so we can actually
see is this fact of fact or not yes is
it sufficient no so if you think about
whatever system if you talk about left
and right brain or mind heart and whale
or all the chakras all the systems of
intelligence and capacity that any
system that looked at what the human
organism is they all need progressively
more developed and then not just the
person with the person with other people
in the environment when you can operate
as a true whole integrated human being
then you can be available to meet in
community so perhaps this next question
will take us a little deeper on this
topic what are the rate limiters that
are unnecessarily slowing down our
ability to live from a state of feeling
interconnected to all life and how do we
remove these rate limiters so that we
quicken humanity's evolution
I think there's an awful lot of
fragmentation in our communication
process you know our message medium to
one another in the form of social media
and Twitter and stuff like that Facebook
and all the rest they they encourage us
to say shorter things and we don't get a
chance to sort of sink into what
somebody really means it's like we're
overwhelmed with this avalanche of
incoming sensory data and most of it is
noise we want to in effect try to come
into the space where we get to have
depth as much as we have frequency
personally I would rather speak to a few
people really really well and have just
acquaintances with a thousand that's a
rate limiter on civilization
I think one of the primary real endures
at the way that we went about
fabricating an identity that worked
particularly in middle school in high
school to be able to allow us to endure
and survive the perhaps of the crisis
that is reality that we live in right
now and of course what that does is that
means you don't engage in a lot of stuff
that we're talking about and that seem
and I guess we might call it ego mind
here tries to protect itself and
inhibits thinking and it reacts to
things and so nothing works if you've
got that in-between unit of people so
that's another major in there the nice
thing about that is it you're actually
needed you can just get rid of it to
turn it off and then go back to being an
authentic dean good so we've got one
last question that's for all three of
you and that is what is your big bet I
know you've formed a think tank called
deep code there's a limited amount of
time there's a limited amount of
resource what's your big bet and were
the biggest leverages do you want to do
functional groups oh god no I think that
for my own part I'm basically having the
hypothesis that there is a theory of
ethics that will allow us to close the
ethical gap that will allow us to move
from consideration of choice effective
choice good choices which is heretofore
been based purely on the notion of
opinion to something which has a
rigorous more mathematical character
which isn't to say that I'm expecting
that choices be made only on the basis
of some intellectual premise but that by
combining the hearts and the value
systems that we have with a toolkit that
allows us to integrate those things in a
sane way that we can move the dialogue
to a position that
is considerably deeper than could be
reached by just simply any single point
of view so in effect I guess you could
say that for me the big bet is whether
or not that ethical system is truly
complete and actually works
I have subjected it to every single test
I can think of I have tried it in my own
business I have tried it in many years
since I have come where become aware of
these concepts and my hope is is that
that is a component a kind of piece of
architecture that that will actually
work that will hold the weight that is
it is in the sense to be placed on it
so I could say something like my big bet
is transforming macroeconomics and the
because economics can be seen as an
interface layer between our worldview
and infrastructure right our worldview
involves things like what do we value
and who are we and what who is other and
who are what are we connected to and
then that's actually codified in an
economic equation where the whale is
worth something that and not something
alive and where oxygen is not worth that
much because there's lots of it and
scare stuff is worth a lot even if we
don't do anything with it right the the
value equation that then predisposes
what we confer resource to if you do
these things will confer more resource
so we confer power that way which then
ends up determining which technologies
get built which is where the physical
power and the Darwinian senses and how
the how the actual planet and each other
are affected we could say that interface
layer right the transition to
internalizing all the externalities and
we could talk about a few processes to
do that we could talk about a real-time
balance sheet of the Commons where we
have sensor grid an Internet of Things
sensor grid and satellites and people
sensor processes that are informing the
built world and the natural world
Commons where they're actually at in
real time how they're changing and so
rather than have separate balance sheets
that are competing at the expense of
each other in increasingly non-viable
win-lose game theory we can actually
work to increase the comprehensive
integrity of the balance sheet of the
Commons and everyone's generative access
to it the you know we can we never had
when Bucky fuller kind of talked about
that as a possibility the ability to
actually have Commons management we
didn't even have internet we didn't have
the Internet of Things right we didn't
have those kinds of data science
capabilities but the technologies that
are both forcing us to change because
they're no longer viable also make
possible change right the technological
unemployment that is both going to in
capitalism as we've known it also makes
it possible to in capitalism as we've
known it and make
the mentally better systems right so
this emergence is both a half-two and
tan at the same time because of
capacities so I could say you know
change of economics but can we change
that without changing infrastructure
where we actually have to build those
kinds of technological systems that
don't fully exist yet we have to build
closed-loop you know material economies
production material economies different
waste management production etc well
they inter affect each other can we
change that without changing worldview
and changing media and education there
are there are theorists that say really
worldview is the main thing and if we
can have a more Omni consider a
worldview if we can have less
dysfunctional ego structures etc that'll
change everything there theorists who
like cultural materialism say actually
the tools in the predisposing behaviors
and if you change the tools that's the
only thing that's really ever changed
anything there are other theorists say
well actually that series of social
system incentives and drivers end up
changing - I see them as inter affecting
and co-arising
and so there is not a solution in there
that is even realizable independent of a
handful of other things that have to Co
arise so the the you know what I'd be
putting my bet on is a minimum necessary
and sufficient set of transforms that
make possible a fundamentally new and
viable civilization structure to answer
that question I had to kind of think
back on what is my big bet like when
have I made a big bet and it's
interesting to notice for me that I'm an
intrinsically a person who operates
through portfolio theory so I don't tend
to make big bets that had to make
distributed risk and a long time ago I
came to the conclusion that the only
viable approach was something called
collective intelligence which is to say
we don't yet know how to do any of the
things that we need to do the only way
to do it is we actually have to learn
first how to be much much better at
knowing how to do things and I worked
really hard on that for a long time
and about four years ago I hit the wall
and I recognized that I could not get
where I wanted to get unless I was going
to place my big bet my big bet was love
which for many people here that may not
seem like that big a thing but you
should understand that up until about
four years ago I actually really didn't
have any friends so that's where quite
serious when I said that friendship is
hard and being willing to go into the
the crucible of love which i think is a
better way of describing it and
exploring all of its dimensionality and
the the pain and the healing and it only
can come through that is that I think is
the big bet
[Applause]
[Music]
you